<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Mayank</title>
<subtitle type="text"></subtitle>
<generator uri="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2018-03-06T22:14:55-05:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Defining Success]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/defining-sucess" />
  <id>/defining-sucess</id>
  <published>2018-03-10T00:00:00-05:00</published>
  <updated>2018-03-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Whether it be academics or athletics or something else, I and many others (or so I believe) have the goal of being &amp;#8216;good&amp;#8217; or &amp;#8216;successful&amp;#8217;. As I am about to embark on a career of science, I have increasingly thought about what that means. Is it well-defined? Is there an objective measure? Or, is it inherently subjective? Does that affect my opportunity to get better?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking about the past, I seem to have been drawn to objective measures of success. For example, I have been a &lt;a href=&#39;/trial-of-miles-miles-of-trials&#39;&gt;competitive runner&lt;/a&gt; for seven years now. The goal there is extremely simple: for a certain distance, minimize the time it takes to run it. One of the best parts of that is that I don&amp;#8217;t have to expend effort in evaluating how good I am. Well, I have to race. But, once the race is done, I have a pretty straightforward conception of how I am doing. Plus, with workouts and training, I can tell whether I am improving on my goal or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a computer scientist, I implicitly think about this using reinforcement learning. Reinforcement learning is a field of machine learning where agents act in an environment and try to maximize some type of reward. Reinforcement learning became popular in the public when Google DeepMind&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href=&#39;https://www.nature.com/articles/nature16961&#39;&gt;AlphaGo defeated Go world champion Lee Sodol&lt;/a&gt;. Reinforcement learning was the workhorse behind DeepMind&amp;#8217;s success. Here, the objective was to win games and the game engine had to explore strategies in order to optimize the probability it won.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the running scenario, my reward function is the time it takes to run a race. The faster I am, the higher my reward. Given that I know this reward function, I can do research and tailor my strategy to increase my reward. That is, to be successful, I just need to get faster and there are canonical ways to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In middle school, I wanted to be good at math. I unfortunately, however, assumed the wrong reward function: math competitions. While I was decently good at them, I &lt;a href=&#39;/rethinking-secondary-mathematics-education&#39;&gt;struggled in the classroom&lt;/a&gt;. The reason being was that I spent my time memorizing all these shortcuts and tricks rather than gain some deep understanding of the mathematical concepts. So, while my goal was to get better at math, the fact that I assumed the wrong reward function and optimized for that means I didn&amp;#8217;t get to the math level I wanted to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the present-day, I do have a better understanding of what it means to be good at math. For example, I know I am much better at proofs and abstraction. But, that is extremely hand-wavey (at least to me). I don&amp;#8217;t have an objective measure for that. Furthermore, while I have a rough understanding of what it takes to to be better, I don&amp;#8217;t have a good definition of the reward function. Thus, while I can get better at math by contributing X hours a day towards it, I probably won&amp;#8217;t be getting better optimally. There is certainly a fear of being inefficient. I want to be able to use the reward function to really understand my strengths and weaknesses so I can create a better strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same uncertainty is happening with my future at a scientist. I need to have a lot of knowledge of the field, but it also requires ability to design experiments, originality, communication, etc. Certain &amp;#8216;objective&amp;#8217; measures have been proposed to measure how good of a scientist someone is. In academia, many of these revolve around citation counts (obviously for industry scientists it is different unless they are constantly publishing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, now we get into the problem of Goodhart&amp;#8217;s Law. It has been paraphrased as &amp;#8220;When a measure becomes a target, it ceases to be a good measure.&amp;#8221; Citation or publication counts can be a good heuristic when someone is not trying to optimize those numbers. But doing can lead to ongoing replication crisis in science where scientists are publishing results of effects that are not actually there. Rather, they employ questionable scientific practices to increase the probability of one statistically significant hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about the great scientists. Galileo, Darwin, Newton, Einstein. Imagine if they were worried about Google Scholar citation counts. They took time to develop highly original and predictive theories that accurately explain reality today. That is science. Yet, many scientists rightfully ask whether someone like Darwin would get a job in academia today? Scientific institutions have defined the reward function in science to be a function of citations and publications, and perhaps the overemphasis of that reward function means science like the greats did won&amp;#8217;t be carried out. Einstein is certainly a highly-cited author, but he is not a top twenty cited scholar in all of physics. It is useful to measure his impact by citation count because he (presumably) was not trying to maximize it. But, as Goodhart&amp;#8217;s Law states, once citation counts becomes a measure of how good a scientist one is, it ceases to be a good measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to think of scientific greatness is via Thomas Kuhn&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;Structure of Scientific Revolutions&lt;/em&gt;. Kuhn is the philosopher of science that popularized the phrase &amp;#8216;paradigm shift&amp;#8217;. He separates science into two distinctions: normal science and revolutionary science. Normal science operates under a paradigm, which is when there is an overarching theory and specific definitions of terminology. This theory makes predictions and scientists are tasked with creating experiments that prove or disprove the theory&amp;#8217;s hypothesis. Revolutionary science is when paradigms change. It seems from Kuhn&amp;#8217;s distinction that the great scientists we have are ones who created new paradigms and brought about revolutionary science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question this brings up is whether the goal of a scientist is to be successful in normal science or bring about a paradigm shift? And, actually, the question is whether those two goals have similar strategies or different strategies? The strategy for success in normal science is straightforward: under the theory, generate hypothesis and conduct experiments confirming or disconfirming the theory. Is doing this how scientists get disillusioned with a current paradigm and create a new one? That is, are the scientists that bring about new paradigms masters of the old one and the best &amp;#8216;normal scientists&amp;#8217; becomes the &amp;#8216;revolutionary scientists&amp;#8217;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason to think this is not true is what oftentimes there is not experimental evidence to support new revolutionary paradigms in the early stages. Rather, it is often held as a dogmatic belief by a few individuals. While history of science taught in layman&amp;#8217;s terms seems to point that new theories were always better predictors than old theories, it is not usually the case. Copernicus&amp;#8217;s heliocentric theory only matched the experimental evidence of Ptolemy&amp;#8217;s geocentric theory more than half a century after Copernicus&amp;#8217;s death. Yet, we praise Copernicus despite the fact he believed in the less experimentally validated theory since it eventually replaced Ptolemy&amp;#8217;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the paradigm shift in artificial intelligence today when deep learning took over. Neural nets were invented a while ago, but they became out of fashion for a while. Yet, it was the &lt;a href=&#39;https://torontolife.com/tech/ai-superstars-google-facebook-apple-studied-guy/&#39;&gt;stubbornness of Geoff Hinton&lt;/a&gt; that led to the advent of the current state of machine learning we see today. Today, we praise Hinton for sticking to his beliefs in the face of pressure to abandon his research. We praise Copernicus for championing the heliocentric theory. And, we praise Lavoisier for replacing phlogiston. Yet, all these scientists had these beliefs when it was seemingly irrational to have them. Thus, there seems to be a degree of irrationality, stubbornness, and close-mindedness it takes to be a great scientist. But before we champion these ideals in scientists, how many scientists had these traits, thought they would be great scientists, and then be proven wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the path for success for revolutionary scientists and normal scientists are in fact different. And, perhaps one is inherently riskier than the other. That risk may lead to a small chance that your name will be in textbooks for generations to come or the much (larger) chance that your theories will be dismissed as hearsay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can turn to philosophy as well to examine the greats there. The great philosophers did not have bulletproof logic. Otherwise, their arguments would be for the most part accepted today. Descartes &lt;em&gt;cogito ergo sum&lt;/em&gt; is influential, but his justification is generally considered inadequate. There are very few dualists in philosophy of mind today. By contemporary standards, Kant&amp;#8217;s arguments would be awful. But, he is considered a great because he changed the way we did philosophy. He gave a new perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In philosophy, like science, we are taught that incremental is good. Yet, being incremental is not how you contribute the most to your field. That is done by being incredibly original. So again we have the question of whether being incremental for some time is necessary for being revolutionary? If not, why do we teach philosophy to be incremental? Some may say yes - it is only after grappling with concepts for years that we are truly able to understand the flaws and generate new ideas and theories. Others might take a more rationalist approach - we are not going to pay attention to the person who generates all these crazy ideas even if it is probable that one of things (unknown to us, though) is influential. Rather, we listen to the person who is trained in the same we are but eventually strays off the path and stakes their reputation on their new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this essay has established anything, it is that I have no idea what it means to be good. Or rather, I can&amp;#8217;t give a precise characterization that lets me optimize my contributions to the field. Perhaps that&amp;#8217;s a good thing. Whenever there is a precise characterization, it oftentimes deviates a little from our intuitive notion of success and we don&amp;#8217;t realize that until we overoptimize the function (and hence become subject to Goodhart&amp;#8217;s Law). While we don&amp;#8217;t have the best metrics for knowing who are the best scientists today, maybe the pursuit of that is ill-fated. We have a general idea of what separates bad science from good science and bad philosophy from good philosophy. Yes we will make mistakes, both by considering bad science to be good science and vice versa. We will probably discover some greats&amp;#8217; works after they die. But this has probably always been the case, from the time of Aristotle to present-day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, it is important to keep on having this conversation so that we are getting better in how we evaluate and making sure we eradicate biases in the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt; I should note that this need not be every runner&amp;#8217;s goal. Something I often see at the collegiate level is that people want to win championships. While this is seemingly similar to my goal, there are slight differences. For example, championship races are often slow because the runners jog for a long time and then have a sprint finish. To be successful in that endeavor requires a lot more sprint speed than needed in my goal. Of course one must be very fast in order to just get to the championship level and there is an overlap between runners who set records and runners who win championships, but I have selectively focused on one.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/defining-sucess&quot;&gt;Defining Success&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on March 10, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reflections on a Year Abroad]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/reflections-on-a-year-abroad" />
  <id>/reflections-on-a-year-abroad</id>
  <published>2017-08-07T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2017-08-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last May, I impulsively decided to study abroad in England for a whole year. I never even truly considered doing so until a week before I had to make my decision. Thankfully, I pushed myself outside of my comfort zone and went for it. Below is a scattering array of reflections of the whole experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At my college were a cohort of study abroad students, most of them from America. Given that we were in similar situations, we bonded quickly - we could talk about our previous years in college, funny British words, and all the political drama that defined the past academic year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I eventually became cognizant of retracting into my bubble of comfort. What is the point of studying abroad if all you do is talk with Americans about American things? I made more of a conscious effort to interact with British students. It was extremely rewarding for I developed an incredible friend group over there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This made me realize how easy it is to fall back into a community where you have so many shared experiences. Growing up, I remember being frustrated at how my parents (who immigrated from India to America) would only have Indian friends. And, it wasn&amp;#8217;t just my parents. I saw this in the Indian-American community as a whole. I understood it was difficult to branch out, but I felt that doing so was definitely feasible and rewarding. My year abroad made me realize just how difficult it is for people born in other countries to do so and how much of an effort one has to put on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the transition from the United States to the United Kingdom is one of the easiest transitions possible. Language barriers are one of the central obstacles of going to a new country, and I experienced very little of that (besides, of course, the funny British words). I can&amp;#8217;t imagine what it would be like for people immigrating from India to America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Born and raised in America, I never felt like I could empathize with immigrants. And if I can&amp;#8217;t as a second-generation American, how should I expect those whose families have been in the country for generations? It&amp;#8217;s easy to make normative statements about how immigrants should act, but the year abroad made me realize that everything was infinitely more complex when you actually live it. Unfortunately, many of these obstacles are difficult to explain. The great philosopher Thomas Nagel advanced the famous argument that we could never understand what it is like to be a bat unless we were actually a bat. I believe one can make a similar claim about the immigrant experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I attempted to sell Swarthmore as the perfect place in &lt;a href=&#39;/advice-on-choosing-an-undergraduate-college&#39;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;, the reality that it has its flaws just like any institution. After a while, it can get overwhelming, and I left last year with many frustrations. This past year abroad made me realize all the great things at Swarthmore that I take for granted. In fact, that was probably a decisive reason for writing that post. Furthermore, some of what I took for granted at Swarthmore are the little things such as Internet reliability, free performances, and a better laundry system. But, you don&amp;#8217;t realize how important the little things are until you don&amp;#8217;t have any of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first term in England was plagued with sickness. Of the nine weeks (it was a trimester system), I was ill for eight. Everything suffered as a result, ranging from academics to running to social activities. I always thought I would heal within 48 hours and never exerted the effort to actively try to get better. It made for a miserable term. The new environment didn&amp;#8217;t help either. Unfortunately, good health is one of the things that everyone takes for granted until they are sick. It&amp;#8217;s a lot better to take the ibuprofen when you&amp;#8217;re feeling a little down rather than go on prescription medicine weeks later. Everyone always realizes this when they are sick but then reverts back to their old mindset once they are better. Good health is often a necessary condition for a positive experience so we really should spend more time being proactive about illnesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right outside my college was a food truck run by two Japanese women. The first few times, I only heard one of the women speak in fluent Japanese with her coworker (daughter, potentially?). Her accent was extremely thick as well. A few months later, I saw her recognize a frequent customer, an old British lady, and she immediately switched to perfect English and a seemingly natural British accent. I was immediately taken aback. Her ability to easily transition between two completely different cultures and be a natural at both left me in a state of awe. To be able to do that is pretty fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main reasons, if not the main reason, I wanted to go to Oxford was the difference in educational pedagogy. Oxford and Cambridge center their learning around the tutorial system. Every week or two, you sit down with a professor and discuss a certain topic for an hour. The exact format depends on both the department and professor. For example, computer science tutorials focus on problem sets and explanations of the solutions. In other subjects, e.g. philosophy, students produce essays every week and some professors choose to make that the main point of discussion of the tutorial while others essentially ignore it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially for my philosophy courses, I felt these one-on-one situations and constant productions of essays solidified my understanding of the material much more than the traditional lecture style elsewhere (though Swarthmore, as a liberal arts college, does a really good job at capping class sizes and making them discussion-based). Furthermore, I came to appreciate what the professors emphasized. It is hard to write an essay per class per week. However, the philosophy professors at Oxford don&amp;#8217;t expect you to write some new original insight every time. Rather, they are almost asking for more of a summary. They want to know that you actually understand the material before you try to build off it. And that makes sense. Philosophy is thousands of years old. Is a twenty year old really going to bring something completely new to the table? While originality is obviously important, I think they recognize there is a limited amount you should expect at the undergraduate level. Rather, actually understand the great philosophers and why their arguments are influential. Unfortunately, the naked pursuit of originality at institutions elsewhere sometimes comes at the expense of misunderstanding the very position you are addressing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone from the European Union can attend Oxford at a domestic cost (at least before Brexit happens). As a result, Oxford has an incredibly international population. English has become the lingua franca of science (and really academia in general) and thus the top researchers in each country flock to the United States and England. But, only there was it cemented in my head how difficult that must be. Imagine giving a lecture on a complex computer science subject in your second or third language! Just because someone struggles does not mean they do not understand the concept. It would be much easier in their native language. I and so many others are lucky to have grown up in a country where the native language is the dominantly spoken language in research. It is that much more impressive when others are at the same level or higher but have come from other countries and faced heavy language barriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before coming to college, I never thought I could live in a big city. Since then, I have spent summers in Philadelphia and New York City and could consider living there in the future. Before this experience, I never thought I could live outside of the United States. Now, I know I could actually consider living in England and potentially even other countries as well. It&amp;#8217;s scary when leaning into discomfort. But, I&amp;#8217;m happy I got to experiment with such a major life change while in college. It gave me just the right amount of exposure to make doing so in the future a feasible option.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reflections-on-a-year-abroad&quot;&gt;Reflections on a Year Abroad&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on August 07, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Eastern Philosophy]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/eastern-philosophy" />
  <id>/eastern-philosophy</id>
  <published>2017-06-11T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2017-06-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;While reading a contemporary philosophy critique, I came across a man named Al-Azm. I was immediately taken aback. I had never seen such a name while reading a philosophical text before. A quick Google search showed that Al-Azm was not some ancient Islamic scholar but rather is a Yale-educated philosopher specializing in the work of Immanuel Kant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the seed in my head was set. I quipped in a &lt;a href=&#39;/from-china-to-tusaloosa&#39;&gt;previous footnote&lt;/a&gt; of mine that a critique I hear about academic philosophy is how Western dominated it is. Eurocentrism is not a new concept. Everyone who has taken a high school history class has heard of it. But philosophers, who pride themselves on rational analysis, should embrace new forms of knowledge. We hope that philosophers are the first removed from irrational biases, though this is clearly not the case as the field remains &lt;a href=&#39;http://www.npr.org/sections/13.7/2013/06/17/192523112/name-ten-women-in-philosophy-bet-you-can-t&#39;&gt;incredibly male-dominated&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In primary and secondary school, we learn about Confucius and Buddha. They seem relatively on par with figures like Aristotle and Descartes. I learned briefly about the Golden Age of Islam just like I did with the Middle Ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In academic philosophy curricula, however, there is no comparison. There are courses just analyzing Plato or Kant or Nietzsche. On the other hand, they will only have a &amp;#8216;Buddhist Philosophy&amp;#8217; class if their department is large enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s take Oxford&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href=&#39;http://www.philosophy.ox.ac.uk/sites/default/files/philosophy/documents/media/Lecture_scheme_2016-17_2_Sept.pdf&#39;&gt;lecture list&lt;/a&gt; for the past year as an example. They planned 102 courses, none of which have an Eastern bent. Now, there ended up being an &amp;#8216;Indian Philosophy&amp;#8217; course this term and a &amp;#8216;Buddhist Philosophy&amp;#8217; course last year, and I suspect the addition of these were not planned but rather the department saw that they had the availability to offer a class. Note also that these two courses are considered special graduate classes and that none of the undergraduate curriculum offers any such courses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, there were two courses (of over a hundred) in the past year explicitly discussing Eastern philosophy. Many of the courses are not necessarily focused on Western figures but rather general themes like &amp;#8220;Philosophy of Science&amp;#8221;. However, I&amp;#8217;m sure that everyone would agree that the curriculum of such classes solely consists of Western philosophers. In fact, this is not necessarily surprising as it might turn out that the Philosophy of Science is a purely Western discipline anyways (though I highly doubt it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a chicken-and-egg problem. If philosophers get educated in the Western tradition, then they will specialize and write about Western concepts. They aren&amp;#8217;t going to start offering Eastern courses because there is not enough faculty to do so. I don&amp;#8217;t think undergraduates would care a lot more about taking Western philosophy classes rather than Eastern. I genuinely believe they would be interested in taking both because almost all of the material they learn will be new to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For lack of a better term, should we then have affirmative action for Eastern philosophy? I suspect that most philosophers realize that the field is inherently Eurocentric. However, there is very little incentive to study &amp;#8220;fringe&amp;#8221; philosophers (in academia) such as Confucius or an Islamic scholar. Their translations might not be as good as the modern Europeans. There is significantly less contemporary literature about them. And, the community is a lot smaller. One has to essentially build Eastern Philosophy from the ground-up, and it is a huge endeavor with little personal payoff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, for a field that prides itself on the love of knowledge, surely philosophy as a whole should embrace, or at least consider, Eastern ideas. Thus, there should be some incentive to bring more Eastern ideas to fruition. It seems such an initiative must happen from universities in order to trump academia politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some may argue that Eastern philosophy follows a significantly different tradition than Western. So what? Philosophy is known as the great debate, and what tradition to follow is definitely fair game to debate. Within Western philosophy, there is the analytical and continental divide. People seem fine with that distinction. Both of those traditions have contributed enormously to the field. Introducing a new way to do philosophy has the potential for huge impact. Great philosophers are those who bring something new to the table. By introducing thinkers from other cultures, one is doing exactly that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others argue that some parts of Eastern philosophy may be too intertwined with religions, for example Islam and Buddhism. The above rebuttal still stands that a different way to do philosophy is insufficient to render it useless. But, more importantly, there is not such a separation between many great Western philosophers and religion. Aquinas, Descartes, and Spinoza each have their own lecture series at Oxford and all three of them were incredibly religious in their philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A high-risk but high-reward venture may be investigating Eastern philosophers for different interpretations of Western philosophies. What if there are other philosophers who developed Kantian philosophies independently? We could use their variations to create new schools of thought and perhaps gain better insights into how to evaluate Kant. Quick Wikipedia searches show that the 12th-century Islamic scholar, Averroes, provided commentaries on Aristotle which eventually influenced Aquinas and is the reason Aristotle is considered a great today. Multiple nineteenth century philosophers noted similarities between Spinoza and the Vedanta school of Indian philosophy. Today&amp;#8217;s philosophers might not want to make the gamble of only doing Eastern philosophy. But, if there are certain philosophies that provide insights into the Western philosophers they study, it could lead to major progress in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be unfair of me to end this post without talking about potential personal conflicts of interest. While I would like to have my argument being as unbiased as possible, I focused on Arabic, Indian, and Chinese philosophies above and my origins are from that area. Despite the little I know about those philosophies, I know even less (i.e. nothing) about African or South American ones and did not reference them. This post was inspired by me reading an Arabic name, but it is unclear whether I would have had the same inspiration with an African name. I do my best to avoid personal biases in my posts, but I reckon it was an important part of this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideological diversity is something I believe almost everyone can accept. For example, I think most Americans would support the idea of bipartisanship. Philosophy is a field which loves knowledge and debates various viewpoints. Shouldn&amp;#8217;t it be one of the first fields, then, to actively seek new insights? Unfortunately, it is not so straightforward to do so and will require the intervention of some university or organization. After all, philosophy is a human endeavor and thus subject to irrational political influences.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/eastern-philosophy&quot;&gt;Eastern Philosophy&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on June 11, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Case for (More) Engineering in Research]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/a-case-for-more-engineering-in-research" />
  <id>/a-case-for-more-engineering-in-research</id>
  <published>2017-05-08T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2017-05-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the past few years, I&amp;#8217;ve been heavily immersed in the academic mindset. I look favorably upon novel research and theory, and I condemn uses of time on what I consider to be not as useful (e.g. excessive programming).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mature, I&amp;#8217;m coming to realize this view of mine is naive at best and flat out wrong at worst. While I still believe novel research is very important, one should not diminish the importance of the engineering and tedious work required to make such progress. Rather, engineering is not only a necessary condition for research but also a massive catalyst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people in math and computer science swear by LaTeX, a typesetting engine that is able math look visually appealing and readable. (If you are not sure what LaTeX is, you will almost surely recognize a document created by it). LaTeX was created by Donald Knuth, one of the greatest theoretical computer scientists. He took on the project because of the awful looking nature of typesetting engines during his time. From start to initial release, LaTeX took over ten years to complete. This is ten years that he could not dedicate to his research. In fact, his research was so advanced that Knuth even received a Turing Award, the &amp;#8220;Novel Prize for Computing.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the question is then: was it worth it? To me and many others in technical fields, LaTeX is an essential part of how we communicate. While newcomers find it difficult to master it in the beginning, it becomes second nature after a few weeks. LaTeX speeds up the process of writing technical results as well as increases the effectiveness of communication: there are little to no ambiguities caused by the typesetting. Rather, we can now just focus on the math. In this regard, I think it&amp;#8217;s clear that LaTeX has helped the field of mathematics and computer science as a whole. I can&amp;#8217;t comment on whether the gains outweigh the ten year loss in Donald Knuth&amp;#8217;s research output. Perhaps we wished a &amp;#8220;lesser&amp;#8221; distinguished academic took on this project. But, I think we are all grateful for the time he spent in engineering this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stanford Professor Fei-Fei Li is the indirect cause of much of the rise in machine learning, especially deep learning: she and her team created ImageNet, a curated dataset of labeled pictures&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:1&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:1&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. While teams originally had to create their own datasets (which were probably smaller and of less quality), Professor Li undertook this project to enable public access to high-quality data. Creation of such a dataset is not necessarily research in itself but rather a tedious effort that research can build off of. As a result, teams can now easily test out the efficacy of their new algorithms instead of spending a lot of time on the dataset. Today, Professor Li is one of the leading figures in the field of artificial intelligence. The question becomes whether this was because of, or despite, the fact that created ImageNet. While it&amp;#8217;s unclear how much it benefited her and her research team, the effect on the machine learning community was huge. A similar argument can be made for NYU&amp;#8217;s Yann LeCun and his creation of the MNIST database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summer after my freshman year, I worked at the University of Pennsylvania under two neuroscience professors. One of them is famous in his subfield for developing the Psychophysics Toolbox, a MATLAB library that facilitates psychophysics experiments. His initial paper, roughly published twenty years ago, has garnered around 9000 citations as of this post. Crudely, this means that around 9000 &lt;em&gt;successful&lt;/em&gt; experiments have been conducted using his toolbox. The benefit his toolbox has brought to the psychophysics research community is clearly huge&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:2&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:2&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Thus, while his single biggest contribution to his research community may be his engineering effort, it has facilitated a large amount of research and thus catalyzed the progress in the field. If he didn&amp;#8217;t lead this project, it seems the field as a whole would not be where it is today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above, I&amp;#8217;ve detailed some examples of how certain academics spent a large amount of time advancing an engineering project rather than their traditional research projects (though there is occasional overlap). It&amp;#8217;s unclear whether their efforts helped their careers. In fact, one could argue it probably reduced their research output, which is the defining standard for academics. But, it is clear that their work greatly benefited their research communities as a whole. These projects are almost altruistic in a way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For research projects to be as efficient and effective as they need to be, somebody must put in the engineering effort. While programming may be looked down upon by some researchers, it probably takes up a significant (if not the majority) time of of the work behind each new publication (at least in the sciences).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question then arises whether incentives in academia are right: where publications trump engineering, but engineering enables more publications in general. It&amp;#8217;s a Nash Equilibrium in a sense. Between the options of focusing on research or research-related engineering, focusing on research is the dominating strategy. If you focus on research while another researcher focuses on research, there is no difference. But if Researcher A focuses on engineering, Researcher B will be have more publications if they focus on research. At best, if the engineering effort is publicly available, Researcher B can expedite the number of publications they produce using that engineering. At worst, if the engineering effort is not publicly available, Researcher B will produce more since Researcher A is spending so much time on the engineering effort. Additionally, Researcher A&amp;#8217;s lab may not be large enough such that the increase in productivity that their engineering enables results in enough papers to make up that lost time. While it&amp;#8217;s a little disheartening to view research as a competitive endeavor rather than collaborative, such can often be the case in academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is there any way incentives can be changed that the research community puts in effort to engineering as well as research? Google Research, DeepMind and Facebook are definitely on this route, but we haven&amp;#8217;t seen it much in traditional academia yet. Is there a way for a researcher to do both effectively? Or, do we need large labs (in industry) where individuals needs to specialize?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are definitely some caveats I should be clear about. First, it may seem that I have framed research and engineering as separate. This is not really the case. Engineering is a necessary part of research. But, from what I can tell, some individuals focus much on the engineering part while others focus on gaining new insights that warrant published papers (often relying on the efforts by those focusing on the engineering). Secondly, I&amp;#8217;m an undergraduate that has not been immersed in research labs. As a result, this is what I see as an outsider looking in. Maybe academics would disagree with me on the state of engineering in research as well as the incentives in the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an ideal world, we want to advance the state of research as quickly and effectively as possible. Engineering that allows efficiency and reproducibility is a big enabler for this. This is not a new problem. Research is dependent on infrastructure, and better infrastructure leads to better research. Is there any way we can better incorporate infrastructural advancements into our current research ecosystem?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#39;footnotes&#39;&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:1&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to undermine all the direct progress she has made on the field. Her research lab is one of the best in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:1&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:2&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other way, albeit crude, to measure the effect would be to count the number of citations of all the papers that cited this toolbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:2&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/a-case-for-more-engineering-in-research&quot;&gt;A Case for (More) Engineering in Research&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on May 08, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spykes]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/spykes" />
  <id>/spykes</id>
  <published>2017-03-31T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2017-03-31T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Spykes is a project I&amp;#8217;m working alongside the &lt;a href=&#39;http://kordinglab.com&#39;&gt;Kording Lab&lt;/a&gt; at Northwestern University. We aim to provide researchers a library that makes analysis and visualization of neural spike trains easy and reproducible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, check out the &lt;a href=&#39;https://github.com/KordingLab/spykes&#39;&gt;github repo&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&#39;http://kordinglab.com/spykes/&#39;&gt;documentation page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/spykes&quot;&gt;Spykes&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on March 31, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advice on Choosing an Undergraduate College]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/advice-on-choosing-an-undergraduate-college" />
  <id>/advice-on-choosing-an-undergraduate-college</id>
  <published>2017-03-29T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2017-03-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently, I&amp;#8217;ve been approached by family friends and others on advice regarding undergraduate college admissions. I spent a pretty significant amount of time researching colleges in high school. I have also been fairly reflective of my three years so far in terms of evaluating whether I made the right choice by coming to Swarthmore. Furthermore, my year abroad at Oxford has allowed me to contrast two very different schools: the small liberal arts college versus the large research institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily for me, my parents essentially gave me complete independence when it came to the college process. I acknowledge this is a luxury, especially in the Indian-American culture. Since most of the people who have sought out my advice are also Indian-American, a lot of what I have to say is in response to the culture&amp;#8217;s narrow viewpoint on college. However, I believe most (if not all) of what I have to say can be applied to anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, do note that I did make the decision to go to a liberal arts college, which is kind of an anomaly in regards to most college-bound seniors and definitely an anomaly among Indian-American students. Therefore, I am probably biased towards small, liberal arts colleges. Also, note that I talk about my personal experience as well as some of my friends. When I talk about my friends, I have changed colleges to preserve anonymity. Lastly, this is not an essay meant to help you get admissions into college. I got into less than half of the schools I applied to. Rather, it&amp;#8217;s advice on how to select schools to apply to and how to decide between multiple acceptances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main question I like to ask every student is why they want to go to college. Frankly, I don&amp;#8217;t think this question is often asked enough. Usually, the students are taken aback and give me some response that is clearly not genuine. Rather it&amp;#8217;s what they believe their parents and college admissions officers want to hear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a lot of the people that surrounded me in high school (including myself), the real answer is that it was always expected of us. It wasn&amp;#8217;t a choice. It&amp;#8217;s like asking us why we want to go to high school, middle school, or elementary school. We didn&amp;#8217;t go because of some romanticized view of learning. Rather, we went because that&amp;#8217;s what we were taught to view as important and the necessary path to follow in the pursuit of achieving the &amp;#8216;good life&amp;#8217;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, there&amp;#8217;s the second answer. No one will every say this answer, but it certainly is in everyone&amp;#8217;s head: prestige. Parents want to be able to say &amp;#8220;My daughter went to Harvard.&amp;#8221; I didn&amp;#8217;t apply to Harvard so I don&amp;#8217;t know if they have a &amp;#8220;Why Harvard?&amp;#8221; essay in its application. If they do, they should remove it because the real answer for almost every single applicant is &amp;#8220;Because It&amp;#8217;s Harvard&amp;#8221;. But, the cunning applicants are able to weave a 200-word narrative that somehow differentiates it from other elite schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prestige is the elephant in the room that people don&amp;#8217;t want to talk about. People often want to go to the most prestigious school for the sake of prestige and bragging rights alone. And, I think all people associated with the applicant want to share the bragging rights. I have a friend who was essentially coerced into picking Yale over Pomona by people they had not talked to in years. Yet, once their acceptances became public, it all of a sudden became everyone&amp;#8217;s business to give their two cents. No one was interested in the merits of Pomona. Rather, &amp;#8220;it&amp;#8217;s Yale&amp;#8221;. I do think that these people had good intentions. But good intentions does not justify influence, especially when it&amp;#8217;s unsolicited. In other words, if people give you advice on college without you asking for it, don&amp;#8217;t listen to them because they probably only care about prestige. I hope that you reading this essay means you are seeking out my advice rather than me giving it out without your consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I hope to do in this essay is remove the appeal associated with prestige. I&amp;#8217;m not advocating for it to be ignored completely. But, I want to show other considerations that should be viewed more importantly. That being said, I believe everyone is vulnerable to prestige. I will be the first one to admit that I am. While Swarthmore was not the most prestigious of schools I was accepted into, I believed it was the best on some of the factors I&amp;#8217;ll talk about below. But, there were certain schools I was wait-listed at that had I received an acceptance from them, I would have taken it over Swarthmore purely because of the prestige. The fact of the matter is that I can lay out an argument for prestige, have you agree with all my points, and acknowledge that prestige shouldn&amp;#8217;t be the most important factor. Yet, by tomorrow, you (and I) will revert back to the prestige mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best example that I like to give why prestige isn&amp;#8217;t everything is the University of Pennsylvania. Obviously, it&amp;#8217;s one of the best schools in the nation. While all elite schools are more or less competitive, Penn is notorious for its cutthroat culture. With rampant grade deflation, students are hypercompetitive because they succeed by beating others. It&amp;#8217;s essentially a zero-sum game (one wonders whether the culture of Wharton has seeped into the whole university&amp;#8217;s).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past four years, Penn has had &lt;a href=&#39;http://www.phillyvoice.com/12th-suicide-less-4-years-hits-upenn-report-says/&#39;&gt;twelve students commit suicide&lt;/a&gt;. This should be shocking. Mental health is increasingly becoming a problem at universities everywhere. But twelve suicides in four years should give every single applicant pause. In the 2009-2010 academic year, Cornell University had six students commit suicide. There are clearly systematic problems with these schools. I fear that people ignore these statistics because of inflated senses of self: the view, &amp;#8220;Oh, this won&amp;#8217;t happen to me.&amp;#8221; But, how many of the students that did commit suicide though that they would when they matriculated? Unfortunately, mental health is an important issue people underestimate unless they or a close one suffer from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, Penn and Cornell are great schools. It&amp;#8217;s not as if suicide is the norm. One must simply go to Wikipedia and see all the notable alumni that demonstrate that these universities produce world-famous graduates. There are tons of great people and groups there. But, I believe the severity of suicide as well as the fact that it is a trend rather than an isolated incident should be of concern. I&amp;#8217;m not saying that one shouldn&amp;#8217;t go to those schools. Rather, troubling statistics like them should be appropriately weighed because they currently aren&amp;#8217;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will concede that the problem may not completely be a toxic culture but also bad mental health resources. Additionally, apparently some elite universities will kick out students for a semester if their mental health is bad enough. That way, it&amp;#8217;ll a) give them time to recover from the toxic environment and b) if anything happens when they&amp;#8217;re away, the university doesn&amp;#8217;t have to take responsibility. After all, elite schools are essentially public relations powerhouses nowadays. Thus, similar schools&amp;#8217; statistics may be deflated and not representative. Regardless, that just shows that other schools may also have a problem, not that Penn and Cornell don&amp;#8217;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So really, ask why you want to really go to college. For me, I eventually picked that I wanted to go for the in-classroom education. I viewed college as four years of intense, formal study that I would never be able to do again. Thus, it&amp;#8217;s no surprise that I then picked a small, liberal arts college. For others, the answer is getting their dream job, having the most opportunities, making a lot of money, etc. I am not going to argue that it&amp;#8217;s more &amp;#8216;noble&amp;#8217; to chase an education rather than money. College is an expensive decision and practical concerns should be just as (if not more) important than romanticized ambitions. But I think everyone&amp;#8217;s answer is different, as it should be. College is a personal decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also probably not just one reason you want to go. In fact, there should be hopefully be multiple. But I want to demonstrate why the answer to this question is important. Say that what I most value is getting a good job right out of college, and I&amp;#8217;d especially like to make a lot of money at the start. If I were in these shoes, the better decision to me would probably have been to go the University of Texas at Austin rather than Swarthmore. They have a top CS program and everyone has heard of them. It is significantly easier to land a job at a tech company with a CS degree from there rather than Swarthmore. I mean, how many tech recruiters have heard of Swarthmore? The amount of tech companies that will actively recruit UT students is incredibly high (and not just because Austin is becoming a tech hub). It&amp;#8217;s one of the top public institutions in the country and a produces a large amount of qualified students. There are probably less than five tech companies that actively recruit at Swarthmore. So if my main goal in life is to become a software engineer at Facebook or Google, then UT should be the pick over Swarthmore. Same if I want to get a job at a &amp;#8220;Big 4&amp;#8221; accounting firm or one of the top management consultancy firms. On the other hand, one of the main reasons I picked Swarthmore was it&amp;#8217;s utter disdain for pre-professionalism. In fact, I viewed it negatively and thus penalized any school where that was a large aspect of the culture. But again, that was a personal decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common fallacy that people make when evaluating colleges is how they evaluate its graduates. It seems relatively straightforward: the best colleges should produce the best graduates. Thus, I should look at the colleges that have the highest paid graduates, most Rhodes scholars, most Fortune 500 CEOs, etc. The problem with these measures is that each university has a different incoming student body with varying levels of strength. It might not be that Stanford helps people become Fortune 500 CEOs. It might just be that they recruit a higher percentage of entrepreneurial students which increases the chance that they have future Fortune 500 CEOs. If those students went to UT Austin, would they have still become Fortune 500 CEOs? Imagine if Amherst replaced its admission staff with the Rhodes scholars&amp;#8217; admissions staff. Wouldn&amp;#8217;t we expect Amherst to have a higher percentage of Rhodes scholars since they are pre-selecting for them? The point I&amp;#8217;m trying to make is that elite universities are not necessarily the ones helping students the most. Rather, the top students may just disproportionately pick the elite universities (which causes a cycle that increases the inequality).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s look at public secondary education as an analogy. Compare the rich suburban high school to the inner-city public school. The suburban high school probably has very high-achieving students who get high standardized test scores and go to prestigious universities. The inner-city public school probably has a high dropout rate. But, I don&amp;#8217;t think you can say that the teachers at the inner-city school are worse than the suburban high school. Rather, the suburban school is better off because its students have certain privileges. They have less non-academic worries because inner-city students might have to also work just to put food on the table. Suburban kids are probably more likely to get expensive tutors if they fall behind in school or need help on standardized tests. The teachers may be better at the inner-city students, but just because the students are so disadvantaged, they don&amp;#8217;t reach the level of success of their suburban counterparts. In fact, it would be significantly easier for the inner-city teachers to go to the suburban school rather than the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the time of matriculation as point A and the time of graduation point B. Too many people are overemphasize point B while under-emphasizing the difference between point A and point B, i.e. the growth. Imagine if college decisions were completely random: that is, everyone gets randomly assigned a college. What would the &amp;#8216;hierarchy&amp;#8217; look like? It would definitely be similar because of lasting effects of prestige. But, I think we can say a priori that the gaps would be much smaller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another mistake that people make is conflating research prowess with good education. &amp;#8220;Columbia has the world-renowned professors, so they&amp;#8217;re the best place to go to because I&amp;#8217;ll learn the most.&amp;#8221; First of all, a professor is not a teacher. A professor is a researcher. They are hired to do research at the university and that is what they are incentivized to do. Teaching is an afterthought for many. A Nobel Prize winner will not be teaching Introduction to Biology. They might teach an upper-level undergraduate class, but even that is not common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, just because you have a lot of knowledge in the field does not mean you are a good teacher. I have a more advanced mathematics background than most elementary school teachers. Who would be better at teaching math to six year olds? Clearly the elementary school teacher. It is not about how well you know the material. It is about how well can you communicate with your intended audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, Oxford is definitely a computer science powerhouse and has some of the leading faculty worldwide. In terms of undergraduate teaching though, the Swarthmore faculty is clearly better. In fact, Swarthmore professors &lt;a href=&#39;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0743731517300114&#39;&gt;publish papers&lt;/a&gt; based on curriculum design. They came to Swarthmore to teach, not to conduct research. As a result, we don&amp;#8217;t expect them to be famous researchers because that&amp;#8217;s not where their priorities lie. Some Oxford professors will often stumble through explanations and advise students to look over the material on their own time afterwards. (Interestingly enough, this might have the effect that you become a better student since you have to learn the material on your own.) Regardless, what is clear is that research prowess should not be considered any type of correlate for the quality of in-classroom education. It is only applicable to those considering graduate school or doing research at the undergraduate level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A case where my argument falters is for the absolute cream of the crop. For example, consider the student who represented the USA in the International Math Olympiad. If they are choosing between MIT and Swarthmore, they should almost certainly go to MIT. They probably prefer a professor who gives them unreasonably hard problem sets with little assistance as opposed to the slower, easier approach you would get at Swarthmore. On the other hand, Swarthmore is great for math students like me, &lt;a href=&#39;/rethinking-secondary-mathematics-education&#39;&gt;who did not come in as very experienced mathematicians&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One piece of advice that I try to emphasize is to not get too fixated on one college. Admissions can very much be a crapshoot. Stanford&amp;#8217;s admissions director came out and said that they could have had a completely new incoming class that would probably been smarter than the one they admitted. Now while the cynic can say this was purely a way of increasing the number of applications (and therefore increasing prestige), I do think it contains a degree of truth. There are just so many qualified applicants that there is a nontrivial degree of luck involved. This is not to say that it&amp;#8217;s complete luck. There are clearly students who deserve to get in and who don&amp;#8217;t deserve to get in. But, even the best students may have a 90% chance of getting in some places (which means a 10% chance of rejection). I know of two Princeton undergrads, one of which didn&amp;#8217;t get into Swarthmore and the other one Duke. The problem is, once people get their decisions, they are labeled into the binary admit/reject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A legal loophole recently allowed students to view their admissions file. I viewed mine at Swarthmore and saw that I wasn&amp;#8217;t a sure bet at all. I was on the edge until one admissions officer gave me the green light and then the others followed. But, now I&amp;#8217;m officially classified as accepted despite the fact I maybe had a 50% (completely arbitrary number) chance of getting in. Consider the Princeton undergrad who maybe had a 90% chance of getting into Swarthmore, but is now labeled as a Swarthmore reject. Maybe the admissions officer reviewing their application had a bad day. Maybe their interests weren&amp;#8217;t aligned with the school&amp;#8217;s. Maybe it was just a coin toss. The fact of the matter is that accept/reject decisions are not necessarily indicative of one&amp;#8217;s ability because you lose a lot of information once you project onto a binary decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I have come across as above prestige, I will be the first one to point out that I&amp;#8217;m not. In fact, while Swarthmore is not well known among tech companies, it has a reputation among academic circles and graduate school admissions. I knew that going to graduate school was very likely for me, and I believed that Swarthmore had a well-earned reputation for sending qualified students there. To me, that prestige was more important than impressing the random passerby at a cocktail party. Furthermore, it would be naive to assume that no sense of prestige was part of my decision to study abroad at Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think prestige is useful and in fact necessary in determining what types of school one should apply to and what should aim for. But, there comes a time when people become hyperaware of this and start defining themselves in terms of where they get accepted or rejected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;College is not an end, but rather a means to the next 80% of your life. I don&amp;#8217;t expect 17 year olds to know exactly what they want to do in life. I most certainty don&amp;#8217;t exactly what I want to do. But, I believe it&amp;#8217;s possible to construct a sense of your values and figure out what colleges most align with those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may be wrong on some points. In fact, I most certainly am. Thus, take everything with a grain of salt. Read my arguments and understand them. Critique and rebut them. I know I consulted a lot of people when I was thinking about schools, and I recommend that you do too. But with more and more people recently asking me for advice, I thought I&amp;#8217;d make what I&amp;#8217;ve learned through the process publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of people will say that &amp;#8220;everything will work out&amp;#8221;. I always thought that as just survivorship bias. But, three years into college, I do really think it&amp;#8217;s true. And, I&amp;#8217;m saying this as someone who got rejected from half of the schools they applied to. I wouldn&amp;#8217;t have done anything differently in high school just to try to increase my chances of getting in some places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who knows, I might have different things to say in five years when I&amp;#8217;m a broke liberal arts college graduate. But until then, I think I can say that Swarthmore was the best decision for me. And it was only because I stopped focusing on prestige.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/advice-on-choosing-an-undergraduate-college&quot;&gt;Advice on Choosing an Undergraduate College&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on March 29, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rethinking Secondary Mathematics Education]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/rethinking-secondary-mathematics-education" />
  <id>/rethinking-secondary-mathematics-education</id>
  <published>2017-02-17T00:00:00-05:00</published>
  <updated>2017-02-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In middle school, I thought I was good at math. I heavily participated in math competitions and was decent at the state level. Those who didn&amp;#8217;t compete would consider me to be smart because I could quickly answer advanced questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, I received C&amp;#8217;s and D&amp;#8217;s in my algebra class. What caused this disconnect between class and competitions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In competitions, I trained to think a specific way. I learned all the tricks of the trade and essentially memorized formulas without understanding any of the logic behind them. After tons of repetitive practice, these formulas became second nature to me. To this day, I can still tell you the square of any number from one to forty. Or, I can tell you how to calculate the area of any regular polygon given its side length. It may seem impressive at first, but in the end it&amp;#8217;s equivalent to memorizing the roster of an NBA team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My memorization of formulas doesn&amp;#8217;t constitute intelligence and that was reflected in my algebra class. That is, I didn&amp;#8217;t know how to actually &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt;. If I didn&amp;#8217;t recognize a problem as the same type of problem I had done a hundred times already, I froze. I wouldn&amp;#8217;t know how to advance. I could not make connections without them being handed to me. Hence the straight C&amp;#8217;s and D&amp;#8217;s as well as getting the lowest grade in the 20+ year &lt;em&gt;history&lt;/em&gt; of my 8th grade math class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, in high school, this got better. I put in extra effort to understand intuitions behind concepts. I wasn&amp;#8217;t focused on memorizing formulas but rather how to use their implications as steps in complex problems. But, I hadn&amp;#8217;t completely transformed. My joy still came from solving problems I knew I could get the answer to by following a systematic set of steps. Give me something using Bayes&amp;#8217; formula and I&amp;#8217;d be the first one to solve it. But give me some abstract formula to prove, and I&amp;#8217;d be stuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I reached college, this started to really become an issue. In my first semester, I enrolled in a twelve person math seminar class where all we did was prove abstract theorems. There was not a single computation in the class. It was about learning how to develop, write, and verbally present rigorous proofs. That class tore me down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, it also built me back up. It has been the hardest, yet most rewarding and memorable class I have taken to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came away with a deep appreciation of what mathematics is really about. I now look forward to proof-based classes because they allow me to grapple with a finite set of axioms in order to reach some conclusion. It requires painstaking hours of deep thinking and is not something that can be rushed at the last minute. Though not as simple as plugging numbers in and getting the desired outcome, it is extremely more gratifying in the long run.&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:1&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:1&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I&amp;#8217;m actually &lt;em&gt;thinking&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Math is often critiqued for not being useful after school. Besides simple calculations with money, we don&amp;#8217;t seem to use it often enough to have justified twelve years of study. I mean, is integration by parts really that useful to those who don&amp;#8217;t go into a technical field? Did I really need to get assigned multiple problems of that nature every day for multiple weeks? No, probably not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barring those who take intermediate or advanced math courses in college, most people believe math is about numbers and computation. But that&amp;#8217;s not really true. One way to define the subject is that it is about creating a set of rules and trying to figure out what logically follows.&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:2&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:2&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High school math education needs to divorce itself from mere number crunching. It should focus on thinking abstractly and giving rigorous proofs. That is, develop the ability to use logic to manipulate your given assumptions. This is what math is about, and it&amp;#8217;s easy to see why it&amp;#8217;s more useful as well. If you are able to produce bulletproof logical arguments, you will succeed in fields from physics to English to law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s true that computation is important. If you can&amp;#8217;t reliably calculate derivatives, how do you expect to manipulate them in proofs? Computation seems like a necessary condition for critical thinking in math. And if it&amp;#8217;s necessary, surely that justifies the emphasis placed on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, there is diminishing marginal returns after a certain amount of focus on computation, and our education system is long past that point. Furthermore, constantly doing proofs can reduce computation errors as it requires students to think much more deeply and rigorously. If they become comfortable with complex series of steps, surely they&amp;#8217;ll develop the ability to do systematic computations as a byproduct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, students have to do computations as intermediate steps in their proofs. If they know what they&amp;#8217;re trying to prove and are not able to do so, it may warrant them reexamining their work and identifying the computation mishap (which is arguably a better teacher than constant repetition).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the onset of computer programming, the ability for humans to compute is becoming less and less important. Yes, students need to understand how to do so and be able to perform them in a reasonable amount of time. But to do them all extremely quickly with a near-perfect accuracy is unnecessary. Formalizing the problem into a series of steps to solve for any input (as you do with programming) suffices to show understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the state of U.S. education, it is improbable that this type of teaching would ever be requested from a federal or state administration. Educators wanting to do so would need to be placed in an ideal scenario: flexibility to develop their own curriculum and students having sufficient knowledge of computation. Also, teachers are often given incentives to teach to standardized tests, so any teacher changing their curriculum to more proof-based would need to be evaluated independently from these tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if teachers are placed in a scenario where these stars align, proofs should be the largest component of their mathematics curriculum. While necessary for analysis, vocabulary and dates are not what English and history are respectively about. Math should be considered in the same light. The subject should be about developing a thought process, not trying to make all students behave as calculators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#39;footnotes&#39;&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:1&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting computation problems can be extremely gratifying in the short term. It&amp;#8217;s analogous to short dopamine bursts people receive when they see a new e-mail in their inbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:1&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:2&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s a relatively large debate about this in philosophy of math literature, which I am unfortunately not (yet) acquainted with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:2&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/rethinking-secondary-mathematics-education&quot;&gt;Rethinking Secondary Mathematics Education&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on February 17, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Have the Empiricists Won?]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/have-the-empiricists-won" />
  <id>/have-the-empiricists-won</id>
  <published>2016-10-31T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-10-31T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two of the hottest buzzwords in the tech industry right now are &amp;#8220;artificial intelligence&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;machine learning&amp;#8221;. Machine learning is a subset of artificial intelligence that can be loosely described as automated data analysis. It promises us less human capital intensive methods to teach computers about the world. I previously talked a little about what machine learning is and its potential applications &lt;a href=&#39;/machine-learning-and-politics&#39;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large companies (e.g. Google, Facebook, Amazon) are slowly monopolizing the machine learning space because they have the single greatest asset: data. Machine learning algorithms are only as good the datasets they are applied on. Create a bigger database and the accuracy of your algorithms soars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way, machine learning researchers differ from traditional statisticians. Statisticians care about accurately describing their confidence level in some statistic of a dataset. Machine learning researchers just want to get the best predictive accuracy humanly possible and will do anything to accomplish this, from running their algorithm on massive clusters to building a bigger dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The renaissance of deep learning has created much of the current hype in artificial intelligence and machine learning. Deep learning is based on neural networks, a biologically-inspired set of functions. These algorithms are all around us today, whether it be Facebook&amp;#8217;s automatic photo tagging or Apple&amp;#8217;s Siri.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been called &amp;#8221;&lt;a href=&#39;http://karpathy.github.io/2015/05/21/rnn-effectiveness/&#39;&gt;unreasonably effective&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221;. Why unreasonably?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, there is actually very little theory behind it. It is not guaranteed to work. Neural networks work by minimizing a given error function. Basic calculus distinguishes between local minima and global minima. The very best solution is at the global minima. Yet, neural networks only find local minima. We hope that the local minima are close to the global minima, but we cannot currently prove that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then why is it so effective? The dataset. Throw enough examples at these networks and they will learn to classify objects. Our solution might not be optimal or mathematically elegant, but it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In pre-Kantian epistemology, the two opposing camps are the rationalists and empiricists. Rationalists, led by Rene Descartes, believe in &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; reasoning. Given a set of assumptions, what can you deduce? On the other side are Hume and the empiricists. This camp prioritizes &lt;em&gt;a posteriori&lt;/em&gt; reasoning, or learning from experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neural networks have so far been on the empiricist side: let&amp;#8217;s observe a lot of data and make conclusions from them. While other machine learning methods have more theory behind them, they still all also tend to be empiricist-based. Without data, they are nothing. University of Washington Professor Pedro Domingos analogized machine learning to the scientific method. Make a hypothesis and collect some data. Refine your hypothesis and repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether we accept that neural networks will lead to an artificial general intelligence or not, it does seem that some combination of machine learning methods will do so. Rule-based (i.e. rationalist) systems have failed in the past and do not achieve an accuracy near modern methods. Empiricists are dominating the field, and it is highly unlikely that data will become less important. Given the vast amount of data we currently have and are generating, why not use it if we can? We have the computing power to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what is happening to the rationalists? They&amp;#8217;ve turned their sights to a new issue: the control problem. Let&amp;#8217;s say we have an artificial agent smarter than humans. How do we make sure its values are aligned with ours? We don&amp;#8217;t want to make foes of these agents. After all, general consensus to why humans have dominated the planet is because of our intelligence. When we lose this monopoly, how do we ensure our survival?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rationalists are working at institutions like the &lt;a href=&#39;https://www.fhi.ox.ac.uk/&#39;&gt;Future of Humanity Institute&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#39;https://intelligence.org/&#39;&gt;MIRI&lt;/a&gt;, trying to assess the existential risk posed by superintelligent agents and how to best avoid such a situation. We can see why an empiricist approach will not work: all it takes is one nonaligned agent to impend world doom. There is no room for error and thus rationalists need to be able to accurately predict and avoid this scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that empiricists have been criticizing rationalists for focusing so heavily on this problem. Two famous machine learning professors, Andrew Ng and Pedro Domingos, have respectively called it an &amp;#8220;unnecessary distraction&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;completely absurd&amp;#8221;. They believe the threat is (1) overhyped and (2) too far away to even worth considering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empiricists and rationalists are not disjoint. While many have a preference for a side, it often takes collaboration from both sides to produce optimal solutions. Elon Musk (who is famous for his rationalist approach of reasoning from first principals) has recently funded OpenAI, a research organization aiming at developing an artificial general intelligence while being cognizant of its risks. So far, the group has been working on reinforcement learning, learning by trial and error - a very empiricist way of learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it does seem that the empiricists have surged ahead of the rationalists at the moment. Itll be interesting to see whether the rationalists will contribute to the lack of theory in the machine learning space or focus more on the existential threat posed by artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much thanks to Rachel Hottle for providing feedback on earlier drafts of this post.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/have-the-empiricists-won&quot;&gt;Have the Empiricists Won?&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on October 31, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Trial of Miles, Miles of Trials]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/trial-of-miles-miles-of-trials" />
  <id>/trial-of-miles-miles-of-trials</id>
  <published>2016-09-03T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-09-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The U.S. has traditionally alternated between two systems: interval-heavy and mileage-heavy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interval-heavy training was popularized through the success of Paavo Nurmi and other Finnish distance runners. In this system you run low mileage but at a high-intensity. After all, to race fast, you need to train fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the other camp, Arthur Lydiard led many New Zealand athletes to success with his mileage-heavy philosophy. He advocates for running many long, moderately-paced miles in order to build up a strong aerobic base. Eventually, speed will come&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:1&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:1&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The systems are not disjoint. The Paavo system has its fair share of mileage buildup, and the Lydiard system definitely incorporates interval training. Practically every competitive distance runner and coach will agree that both types of training are necessary for success. The difference in training programs is their emphasis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current trend (at least in American distance running) is the Lydiard system and has been the training philosophy I have followed for the extent of my running &amp;#8220;career&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training plans are relatively straightforward:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run six to seven days a week.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;One day (usually Sunday) is dedicated to a &amp;#8220;long run&amp;#8221;, which comprises 20% - 25% of weekly mileage&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Two to three days are dedicated to workouts, which are high-intensity work (e.g. 10x400m at mile pace with 90 second rest, 5 continuous miles a little slower than race pace, etc.). Usually one is a shorter distance (e.g. 400m) and the other is longer (e.g. 1000m).&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;For the rest of the days, jog to recover and build mileage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many variations on this. Some people will take their long runs fast. For others, their easy jogs are not easy (at least by my standards) at all. Different training groups also have different emphases: long run can be the most important workout for some, while others care the most about 1000m repeats. But, the list above are the basis of essentially every program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the reason there is so much variation is because each runner responds to a different stimulus. Some need high-mileage. Others&amp;#8217; bodies break down at that point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to show how inconsistent this can all be, here is a graph of my weekly running mileage since freshman year of college.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#39;center&#39;&gt;
  &lt;img align=&#39;center&#39; src=&#39;/images/mileage.png&#39; width=&#39;25%&#39; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dots indicate races I&amp;#8217;ve run. Red means bad, yellow alright, and green is good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The four drops to zero miles are the one to two week breaks I take after the end of cross country and track seasons. Using these drops, we can break the graph into five curves:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freshman Cross Country&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Freshman Indoor Track + Outdoor Track&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Sophomore Summer + Cross Country&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Sophomore Indoor Track + Outdoor Track&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Junior Summer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My freshman year was horrendous: one good race, one alright race, six bad races. But, it was followed by a breakout sophomore year. I still don&amp;#8217;t know what caused my huge success The paradox is that mileage and workouts were relatively similar. Sleep and a few other variables were slightly better my sophomore year, but it doesn&amp;#8217;t seem sufficient for a breakout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the questions I ask myself is whether the mileage buildup I had my freshman year, which doubled my high school weekly mileage, resulted in short-term failures but longer-term success. It is my current hypothesis, but again it doesn&amp;#8217;t seem sufficient in itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fifth, unfinished curve represents my current buildup coming into junior year cross country. I have focused on slow mileage building, but I am in significantly worse shape than the same time my sophomore year. It&amp;#8217;s hard to compare because I have not done workouts or races yet, so I may be fine. But if not, it&amp;#8217;s hard to see why the summer coming into my sophomore year was so much more successful than the one coming into my junior year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good, bad, and alright races also seem unpredictable. Whether or not I take a down week (i.e. downward sloping on the graph) does not have a definitive effect. That being said, the sample size is so small it&amp;#8217;s hard to make any judgments from it alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My whole point for this post is that running is complicated&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:2&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:2&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Success is easily defined: how fast can you run. But, no one has figured out the science behind becoming faster. It takes a combination of mileage and interval training, but to what extent in each direction? Also, there are so many other factors affecting races: weather, mental state, sleep, and luck just to name a few. However, I think these deviations are more prevalent in runners than other sports because of the small sample size of races and that success is based on an individual (see: Law of Large Numbers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#39;/machine-learning-and-politics&#39;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, I discussed the dichotomy between the hedgehog and the fox. For individuals or small training groups, one needs to be a fox and tailor plans to the specific athlete. It&amp;#8217;s important to note that Paavo Nurmi and Arthur Lydiard (the godfathers of the two schools of running) were more fox-ish (I couldn&amp;#8217;t bring myself to say foxy) than we make them out to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hedgehogs, those who believe in big ideas, do indeed have success in the running world. But, it&amp;#8217;s when they have a huge team and just run them through a system. With enough runners, there will be some who emerge as stars. High school running powerhouses are notorious for doing this. However, because the training wasn&amp;#8217;t catered to the individual, their athletes usually fall short of expectations in college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the small dataset of training and its impact on races, no one has determined a set formula to succeed. Perhaps a larger dataset will shed light into the science of the subject. But perhaps there is an art involved, and that&amp;#8217;s what makes it so alluring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;div class=&#39;footnotes&#39;&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:1&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did not mean to make it sound Field of Dreams - esque&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:1&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:2&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know of a runner from DI running powerhouse, University of Portland. Despite the fact that he ran 120 miles per week (40 - 50 more than me), our collegiate personal bests in the 5000m are equivalent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:2&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/trial-of-miles-miles-of-trials&quot;&gt;The Trial of Miles, Miles of Trials&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on September 03, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Machine Learning and Politics]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/machine-learning-and-politics" />
  <id>/machine-learning-and-politics</id>
  <published>2016-08-21T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-08-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Machine learning promises us precise and accurate predictions. From the past movies youve seen on Netflix, what will you want to see in the future? Depending on your genetic makeup, what treatment should you take? Based on the current game board in Go, what is the best move to play?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Policymakers are becoming increasingly split on party lines among how to best allocate resources. In &lt;em&gt;Whatever It Takes&lt;/em&gt;, Paul Tough describes the age-old question on how to solve the educational achievement gap. Conservatives believe those in the low-income bracket are lazy, while liberals attribute their failures to insufficient government support. The debate on the relationship between education and poverty is ongoing, and as a result, we dont have a definitive way of using education to end the poverty cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter machine learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning may actually be able to determine the cause of the achievement gap. Imagine a longitudinal study that tracks as much student data as possible. Im talking data ranging from their IQ to the zip code they were born in to the background of their family members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we get all this data, unleash learning algorithms on them. Well try to predict an attribute like a student&amp;#8217;s test scores or whether they graduate from college. If our learner has a decent accuracy rate, we may have solved the achievement gap. Now, just start with a target student and tweak their characteristics to see what results in higher scores or a better graduation rate. Policymakers will then finally understand what exactly we need to change instead of relying on &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; intuitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now yes, there are many caveats here. First, we need to get an enormous amount of data for this experiment to work. Is it possible to do get enough data that does not violate privacy concerns but is able to sufficiently train the learner? Next, our learner is not guaranteed to be a good predictor. If not, is it because the problem is unsolvable or we dont have enough data? And perhaps most importantly, even if we train an accurate learner, will policymakers concede if they disagree with it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are essential questions to address, but I dont think they should obscure the bigger picture: machine learning has the potential to greatly reduce partisan gridlock in Congress! Policy aims to solve problems, and its often unclear that it actually does. In an ideal world, policy isnt about rhetoric but rather delivering tangible results. Machine learning may very well be our best shot to figure out what is the right thing to do. If we accept that actual progress is more important than saving face, machine learning will change policy work drastically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Nate Silver recounts in &lt;em&gt;The Signal and the Noise&lt;/em&gt;, there are hedgehogs and foxes. Hedgehogs, like politicians, believe one theory explains everything. Foxes, on the other hand, believe that there are many variables you must look at. He attributes much of his success&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:1&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:1&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; with election predictions to his foxlike nature. Machine learning promises to be a fox and analyze the minute details. If trained right, it will understand what variables &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; affect problems like the achievement gap and thus give us detailed recommendations on how to end it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the excitement of machine learning has been with science and software companies. But, governments have a lot to gain by deploying such algorithms on us&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:2&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:2&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Yes, there are privacy issues to be considered. Yes, algorithms probably will not bring closure on issues like abortion and the death penalty. And yes, there will still be debates about how to best implement the proposed solutions. But, it is definitely within our reach to solve problems like the achievement gap. That in itself is enough justification to use machine learning in the policy world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;div class=&#39;footnotes&#39;&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:1&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is, before Trump&amp;#8217;s GOP Nomination&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:1&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:2&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is in no way an endorsement of the NSA data-collection scheme. There is some personal data that should be analyzed and some that shouldn&amp;#8217;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:2&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/machine-learning-and-politics&quot;&gt;Machine Learning and Politics&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on August 21, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[RoboTutor]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/robotutor" />
  <id>/robotutor</id>
  <published>2016-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;RoboTutor is a project at Carnegie Mellon&amp;#8217;s Robotics Institute aiming to enable students ages 7 - 10 with basic arithmetic, reading, and writing skills. This project is the university&amp;#8217;s entry into the Global Learning XPRIZE Competition, which is aiming to solve the shortage of teachers in developing countries through open-source technology. I designed and implemented the tutor for addition, subtraction, and multiplication. In addition, I designed the persona of the tutor that will act as a motivational agent to the student throughout the learning process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked on this project under the supervision of Professor &lt;a href=&#39;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~mostow/&#39;&gt;Jack Mostow&lt;/a&gt;. For more information, &lt;a href=&#39;http://www.cmu.edu/scs/robotutor/&#39;&gt;click here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/robotutor&quot;&gt;RoboTutor&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on August 04, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[From China to Tuscaloosa]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/from-china-to-tuscaloosa" />
  <id>/from-china-to-tuscaloosa</id>
  <published>2016-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When someone talks about &amp;#8220;zen&amp;#8221;, the last thing you think about is college football. Especially good ole&amp;#8217; SEC football. But, there is an interesting life philosophy that connects the Zen master and ancient Greeks to the California mountain climbers and Alabama football players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yvon Chouninard, avid climber and founder of the Patagonia clothing company, writes in his memoir, &lt;em&gt;Let My People Go Surfing&lt;/em&gt;, that he has&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;been a student of Zen philosophy of many years. In Zen archery, for example, you forget about the goal - hitting the bull&amp;#8217;s eye - and instead focus on all the individual movements involved in shooting an arrow. You practice your stance, reaching back and smoothly pulling an arrow out of the quiver, notching it on the string, controlling your breathing, and letting the arrow release itself. If you&amp;#8217;ve perfected all the elements, you can&amp;#8217;t help but hit the center of the target. The same philosophy is true for climbing mountains. If you focus on the &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; of climbing, you&amp;#8217;ll end up on the summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For college football fans, this concept of focusing on the &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; may seem all too familiar. Nick Saban, legendary coach of the Alabama Crimson Tide, has made it a trademark of his coaching philosophy ever since being introduced to the concept by a Michigan State psychology professor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, the input is what matters. It is the only thing you can control. Focus on doing your role, step by step, and the rest will fall into place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monte Burke explains in his biography, &lt;em&gt;Saban: The Making of a Coach&lt;/em&gt;, that &amp;#8220;Saban constantly admonished his players not to think about lifting a trophy at the end of the season, but focus on conditioning, reps in practice, and on keeping their grades up to remain eligible to play.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#39;http://www.secsports.com/article/14561357/nick-saban-process&#39;&gt;SEC Sports article&lt;/a&gt; states that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Process is simply Saban&amp;#8217;s core belief that the willingness to prepare in a methodical, daily basis is the key to success. Saban believes those who focus on the result and not the consistent preparation that is necessary to achieve the result are doomed to be disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;It&amp;#8217;s about committing yourself to being the best you can be on that particular day,&amp;#8221; said Saban. &amp;#8220;Improvement is a steady march and you have to be committed to it.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ryan Holiday drew parallels between &amp;#8216;the Process&amp;#8217; and Stoic philosophy in his book, &lt;em&gt;The Obstacle is the Way&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:1&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:1&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Stoicism advocates for not letting the results of actions dictate your feelings. Results are products of your inputs as well as some other, uncontrollable inputs. If these uncontrollable inputs go against you, failure is not necessarily your fault. Thus, if you are doing the best to your ability and still fail, so be it. There is a degree of luck involved in the success of every venture, and one must obey the laws of probability.&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:2&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:2&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until I read Chouinard&amp;#8217;s memoir, I thought &amp;#8216;the Process&amp;#8217; was a relatively obscure and isolated idea. The fact that it is a part of Zen philosophy and mountain climbing culture, in addition to SEC football and Stoicism, just might point to the range and importance of the concept. It is an effective and successful philosophy that can and should be used by anyone with a goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common criticism I hear of American philosophy departments is that they only emphasize Western philosophy. It would be interesting learning more about Eastern philosophies or more obscure Western philosophies (e.g. Stoicism) to learn about new ideas and potential parallels. It may even increase the popularity of philosophy.&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:3&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:3&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;div class=&#39;footnotes&#39;&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:1&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stoicism is often misrepresented as showing no emotion and having no feeling. It is much more complex than this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:1&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:2&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Referencing probability while explaining a philosophy is what happens when you read too much Eliezer Yudkowsky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:2&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:3&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t mind philosophy being considered impractical, but I&amp;#8217;m also a philosophy minor. That being said, the ratio of computer science to philosophy majors at my school is 16:1, and I go to a liberal arts college.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:3&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/from-china-to-tuscaloosa&quot;&gt;From China to Tuscaloosa&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on June 02, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lies, Damned Lies, and Statistics]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/lies-damned-lies-and-statistics" />
  <id>/lies-damned-lies-and-statistics</id>
  <published>2016-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With big data and numbers pervading into social science research nowadays, it is becoming increasingly important that we start educating individuals on how to create and interpret statistical inferences. Too many times an author will (perhaps unintentionally) use ambiguous language to suggest a conclusion that does not actually follow from their data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago, I read Michelle Alexander&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;The New Jim Crow: Mass Incarceration in the Age of Colorblindness&lt;/em&gt;. This book truly lived up to all the hype and is a must-read for anyone who has ever pondered about mass incarceration and the criminal justice system in the United States today. Alexander lays out her bold conclusion upfront, but she backs up it well in her arguments throughout the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My inner statistician, however, did pick up on some questionable uses of data. While these points were very minor compared to the scope of the whole book, they serve as good examples of the potential to misinterpret statistics in current literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During one instance, she pointed how &amp;#8220;white youth were actually the &lt;em&gt;most likely&lt;/em&gt; of any racial or ethnic group to be guilty of illegal drug possession.&amp;#8221; It is easy to glance over this statement and think that it is straightforward, but her language describing her data is actually ambiguous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, two different interpretations are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A larger percentage of white youth population possesses illegal drugs compared to the black youth population&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that a youth possesses drugs, they have a higher chance of being white than black&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First glance of the original statement seems to point to (1), but her data could actually represent (2). And, if the latter is the case, the statement is trivial. There are more white youths than black youths in the United States. If drug possession is identically distributed among the races, we expect more illegal drug possessors will be white rather than black due to population demographics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I believe Alexander wrote the original statement to support the claim that black youth aren&amp;#8217;t worse than white youth, it can be interpreted at first glance to be arguing that white youth are worse than black youth. It is unclear what she means, and statements of this magnitude need to be rigorously backed up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexander similarly remarks later that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, in New Jersey, whites were almost twice as likely to be found with illegal drugs or contraband as African Americans, and few times as likely to be found with contraband as Latinos. Although whites were more likely to be guilty or carrying drugs, they were far less likely to be viewed as suspicious, resulting in relatively few stops, searches, and arrests of whites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, the first half of this statement is as ambiguous as the previous example - it can definitely fall under either interpretation. I believe the point she wishes to make is that there is a discrepancy between actual drug possession and police searching. This conclusion is valid and follows from her presentation of the data. However, again, it is easy for the reader to gather that whites are the worst racial group when it comes to drug usage. There is nothing wrong with that statement if it&amp;#8217;s true, but it is unclear from her language if it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to completely criticize Alexander, I did applaud her for pointing out one statistical misinterpretation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As much as half of state prisoners are violet offenders, but that statistic can easily be misinterpreted. Violent offenders tend to get longer prison sentences that nonviolent offenders, and therefore comprise a much larger share of the prison population than they would if they had earlier release dates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexander highlights that data is not i.i.d. (independently, identically distributed). Rather, each prisoner does not have the same sentence length. Thus, any statistic that aggregates the state of a prison at any one instance is not representative of the prison system because those with longer sentences are overrepresented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vague statistical language can imply certain conclusions when they actually mean something different. It is both up to the writer and the reader to be skeptical and closely analyze any such use. Too many times members of the media, especially news organizations, can spin numbers to fit their agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On an ending note, &lt;em&gt;The New Jim Crow&lt;/em&gt; is a phenomenal book and has established Alexander as a key civil rights advocate of this decade. The amount of racism in the law enforcement and criminal justice system is at too high of a level. While we have made so much progress over the past fifty years, it is obviously not enough.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lies-damned-lies-and-statistics&quot;&gt;Lies, Damned Lies, and Statistics&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on May 20, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[GreenMon]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/greenmon" />
  <id>/greenmon</id>
  <published>2016-05-19T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;GreenMon is a peer-to-peer cluster management system designed to reduce power consumption. It dynamically powers nodes on and off in response to changing system usage. Benefits of peer-to-peer compared to the usual model of cluster with a master node include both better scalability and fault tolerance. GreenMons protocols utilize randomization to bypass any additional communication between nodes and thus keep the system lightweight. While ideally designed for remote clusters, it is general enough to be used on any LAN cluster. Preliminary simulations show that GreenMon can reduce power consumption by eighty percent on a schoolwide lab cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked on this project alongside classmates Owen Kephart and Oscar Chen. We were lucky to work under the guidance of &lt;a href=&#39;https://www.cs.swarthmore.edu/~newhall/&#39;&gt;Tia Newhall&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#39;https://www.cs.swarthmore.edu/~knerr/&#39;&gt;Jeff Knerr&lt;/a&gt;. The full paper is &lt;a href=&#39;/assets/docs/greenmon.pdf&#39;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenmon&quot;&gt;GreenMon&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on May 19, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>