<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Mayank</title>
<subtitle type="text"></subtitle>
<generator uri="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2017-02-17T05:10:22-05:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rethinking Secondary Mathematics Education]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/rethinking-secondary-mathematics-education" />
  <id>/rethinking-secondary-mathematics-education</id>
  <published>2017-02-17T00:00:00-05:00</published>
  <updated>2017-02-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In middle school, I thought I was good at math. I heavily participated in math competitions and was decent at the state level. Those who didn&amp;#8217;t compete would consider me to be smart because I could quickly answer advanced questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, I received C&amp;#8217;s and D&amp;#8217;s in my algebra class. What caused this disconnect between class and competitions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In competitions, I trained to think a specific way. I learned all the tricks of the trade and essentially memorized formulas without understanding any of the logic behind them. After tons of repetitive practice, these formulas became second nature to me. To this day, I can still tell you the square of any number from one to forty. Or, I can tell you how to calculate the area of any regular polygon given its side length. It may seem impressive at first, but in the end it&amp;#8217;s equivalent to memorizing the roster of an NBA team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My memorization of formulas doesn&amp;#8217;t constitute intelligence and that was reflected in my algebra class. That is, I didn&amp;#8217;t know how to actually &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt;. If I didn&amp;#8217;t recognize a problem as the same type of problem I had done a hundred times already, I froze. I wouldn&amp;#8217;t know how to advance. I could not make connections without them being handed to me. Hence the straight C&amp;#8217;s and D&amp;#8217;s as well as getting the lowest grade in the 20+ year &lt;em&gt;history&lt;/em&gt; of my 8th grade math class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, in high school, this got better. I put in extra effort to understand intuitions behind concepts. I wasn&amp;#8217;t focused on memorizing formulas but rather how to use their implications as steps in complex problems. But, I hadn&amp;#8217;t completely transformed. My joy still came from solving problems I knew I could get the answer to by following a systematic set of steps. Give me something using Bayes&amp;#8217; formula and I&amp;#8217;d be the first one to solve it. But give me some abstract formula to prove, and I&amp;#8217;d be stuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I reached college, this started to really become an issue. In my first semester, I enrolled in a twelve person math seminar class where all we did was prove abstract theorems. There was not a single computation in the class. It was about learning how to develop, write, and verbally present rigorous proofs. That class tore me down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, it also built me back up. It has been the hardest, yet most rewarding and memorable class I have taken to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came away with a deep appreciation of what mathematics is really about. I now look forward to proof-based classes because they allow me to grapple with a finite set of axioms in order to reach some conclusion. It requires painstaking hours of deep thinking and is not something that can be rushed at the last minute. Though not as simple as plugging numbers in and getting the desired outcome, it is extremely more gratifying in the long run.&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:1&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:1&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I&amp;#8217;m actually &lt;em&gt;thinking&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Math is often critiqued for not being useful after school. Besides simple calculations with money, we don&amp;#8217;t seem to use it often enough to have justified twelve years of study. I mean, is integration by parts really that useful to those who don&amp;#8217;t go into a technical field? Did I really need to get assigned multiple problems of that nature every day for multiple weeks? No, probably not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barring those who take intermediate or advanced math courses in college, most people believe math is about numbers and computation. But that&amp;#8217;s not really true. One way to define the subject is that it is about creating a set of rules and trying to figure out what logically follows.&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:2&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:2&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High school math education needs to divorce itself from mere number crunching. It should focus on thinking abstractly and giving rigorous proofs. That is, develop the ability to use logic to manipulate your given assumptions. This is what math is about, and it&amp;#8217;s easy to see why it&amp;#8217;s more useful as well. If you are able to produce bulletproof logical arguments, you will succeed in fields from physics to English to law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s true that computation is important. If you can&amp;#8217;t reliably calculate derivatives, how do you expect to manipulate them in proofs? Computation seems like a necessary condition for critical thinking in math. And if it&amp;#8217;s necessary, surely that justifies the emphasis placed on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, there is diminishing marginal returns after a certain amount of focus on computation, and our education system is long past that point. Furthermore, constantly doing proofs can reduce computation errors as it requires students to think much more deeply and rigorously. If they become comfortable with complex series of steps, surely they&amp;#8217;ll develop the ability to do systematic computations as a byproduct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, students have to do computations as intermediate steps in their proofs. If they know what they&amp;#8217;re trying to prove and are not able to do so, it may warrant them reexamining their work and identifying the computation mishap (which is arguably a better teacher than constant repetition).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the onset of computer programming, the ability for humans to compute is becoming less and less important. Yes, students need to understand how to do so and be able to perform them in a reasonable amount of time. But to do them all extremely quickly with a near-perfect accuracy is unnecessary. Formalizing the problem into a series of steps to solve for any input (as you do with programming) suffices to show understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the state of U.S. education, it is improbable that this type of teaching would ever be requested from a federal or state administration. Educators wanting to do so would need to be placed in an ideal scenario: flexibility to develop their own curriculum and students having sufficient knowledge of computation. Also, teachers are often given incentives to teach to standardized tests, so any teacher changing their curriculum to more proof-based would need to be evaluated independently from these tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if teachers are placed in a scenario where these stars align, proofs should be the largest component of their mathematics curriculum. While necessary for analysis, vocabulary and dates are not what English and history are respectively about. Math should be considered in the same light. The subject should be about developing a thought process, not trying to make all students behave as calculators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#39;footnotes&#39;&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:1&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting computation problems can be extremely gratifying in the short term. It&amp;#8217;s analogous to short dopamine bursts people receive when they see a new e-mail in their inbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:1&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:2&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s a relatively large debate about this in philosophy of math literature, which I am unfortunately not (yet) acquainted with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:2&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/rethinking-secondary-mathematics-education&quot;&gt;Rethinking Secondary Mathematics Education&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on February 17, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Have the Empiricists Won?]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/have-the-empiricists-won" />
  <id>/have-the-empiricists-won</id>
  <published>2016-10-31T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-10-31T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two of the hottest buzzwords in the tech industry right now are &amp;#8220;artificial intelligence&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;machine learning&amp;#8221;. Machine learning is a subset of artificial intelligence that can be loosely described as automated data analysis. It promises us less human capital intensive methods to teach computers about the world. I previously talked a little about what machine learning is and its potential applications &lt;a href=&#39;/machine-learning-and-politics&#39;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large companies (e.g. Google, Facebook, Amazon) are slowly monopolizing the machine learning space because they have the single greatest asset: data. Machine learning algorithms are only as good the datasets they are applied on. Create a bigger database and the accuracy of your algorithms soars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way, machine learning researchers differ from traditional statisticians. Statisticians care about accurately describing their confidence level in some statistic of a dataset. Machine learning researchers just want to get the best predictive accuracy humanly possible and will do anything to accomplish this, from running their algorithm on massive clusters to building a bigger dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The renaissance of deep learning has created much of the current hype in artificial intelligence and machine learning. Deep learning is based on neural networks, a biologically-inspired set of functions. These algorithms are all around us today, whether it be Facebook&amp;#8217;s automatic photo tagging or Apple&amp;#8217;s Siri.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been called &amp;#8221;&lt;a href=&#39;http://karpathy.github.io/2015/05/21/rnn-effectiveness/&#39;&gt;unreasonably effective&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221;. Why unreasonably?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, there is actually very little theory behind it. It is not guaranteed to work. Neural networks work by minimizing a given error function. Basic calculus distinguishes between local minima and global minima. The very best solution is at the global minima. Yet, neural networks only find local minima. We hope that the local minima are close to the global minima, but we cannot currently prove that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then why is it so effective? The dataset. Throw enough examples at these networks and they will learn to classify objects. Our solution might not be optimal or mathematically elegant, but it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In pre-Kantian epistemology, the two opposing camps are the rationalists and empiricists. Rationalists, led by Rene Descartes, believe in &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; reasoning. Given a set of assumptions, what can you deduce? On the other side are Hume and the empiricists. This camp prioritizes &lt;em&gt;a posteriori&lt;/em&gt; reasoning, or learning from experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neural networks have so far been on the empiricist side: let&amp;#8217;s observe a lot of data and make conclusions from them. While other machine learning methods have more theory behind them, they still all also tend to be empiricist-based. Without data, they are nothing. University of Washington Professor Pedro Domingos analogized machine learning to the scientific method. Make a hypothesis and collect some data. Refine your hypothesis and repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether we accept that neural networks will lead to an artificial general intelligence or not, it does seem that some combination of machine learning methods will do so. Rule-based (i.e. rationalist) systems have failed in the past and do not achieve an accuracy near modern methods. Empiricists are dominating the field, and it is highly unlikely that data will become less important. Given the vast amount of data we currently have and are generating, why not use it if we can? We have the computing power to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what is happening to the rationalists? They&amp;#8217;ve turned their sights to a new issue: the control problem. Let&amp;#8217;s say we have an artificial agent smarter than humans. How do we make sure its values are aligned with ours? We don&amp;#8217;t want to make foes of these agents. After all, general consensus to why humans have dominated the planet is because of our intelligence. When we lose this monopoly, how do we ensure our survival?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rationalists are working at institutions like the &lt;a href=&#39;https://www.fhi.ox.ac.uk/&#39;&gt;Future of Humanity Institute&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#39;https://intelligence.org/&#39;&gt;MIRI&lt;/a&gt;, trying to assess the existential risk posed by superintelligent agents and how to best avoid such a situation. We can see why an empiricist approach will not work: all it takes is one nonaligned agent to impend world doom. There is no room for error and thus rationalists need to be able to accurately predict and avoid this scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that empiricists have been criticizing rationalists for focusing so heavily on this problem. Two famous machine learning professors, Andrew Ng and Pedro Domingos, have respectively called it an &amp;#8220;unnecessary distraction&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;completely absurd&amp;#8221;. They believe the threat is (1) overhyped and (2) too far away to even worth considering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empiricists and rationalists are not disjoint. While many have a preference for a side, it often takes collaboration from both sides to produce optimal solutions. Elon Musk (who is famous for his rationalist approach of reasoning from first principals) has recently funded OpenAI, a research organization aiming at developing an artificial general intelligence while being cognizant of its risks. So far, the group has been working on reinforcement learning, learning by trial and error - a very empiricist way of learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it does seem that the empiricists have surged ahead of the rationalists at the moment. It’ll be interesting to see whether the rationalists will contribute to the lack of theory in the machine learning space or focus more on the existential threat posed by artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much thanks to Rachel Hottle for providing feedback on earlier drafts of this post.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/have-the-empiricists-won&quot;&gt;Have the Empiricists Won?&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on October 31, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Trial of Miles, Miles of Trials]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/trial-of-miles-miles-of-trials" />
  <id>/trial-of-miles-miles-of-trials</id>
  <published>2016-09-03T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-09-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The U.S. has traditionally alternated between two systems: interval-heavy and mileage-heavy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interval-heavy training was popularized through the success of Paavo Nurmi and other Finnish distance runners. In this system you run low mileage but at a high-intensity. After all, to race fast, you need to train fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the other camp, Arthur Lydiard led many New Zealand athletes to success with his mileage-heavy philosophy. He advocates for running many long, moderately-paced miles in order to build up a strong aerobic base. Eventually, speed will come&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:1&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:1&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The systems are not disjoint. The Paavo system has its fair share of mileage buildup, and the Lydiard system definitely incorporates interval training. Practically every competitive distance runner and coach will agree that both types of training are necessary for success. The difference in training programs is their emphasis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current trend (at least in American distance running) is the Lydiard system and has been the training philosophy I have followed for the extent of my running &amp;#8220;career&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training plans are relatively straightforward:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run six to seven days a week.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;One day (usually Sunday) is dedicated to a &amp;#8220;long run&amp;#8221;, which comprises 20% - 25% of weekly mileage&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Two to three days are dedicated to workouts, which are high-intensity work (e.g. 10x400m at mile pace with 90 second rest, 5 continuous miles a little slower than race pace, etc.). Usually one is a shorter distance (e.g. 400m) and the other is longer (e.g. 1000m).&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;For the rest of the days, jog to recover and build mileage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many variations on this. Some people will take their long runs fast. For others, their easy jogs are not easy (at least by my standards) at all. Different training groups also have different emphases: long run can be the most important workout for some, while others care the most about 1000m repeats. But, the list above are the basis of essentially every program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the reason there is so much variation is because each runner responds to a different stimulus. Some need high-mileage. Others&amp;#8217; bodies break down at that point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to show how inconsistent this can all be, here is a graph of my weekly running mileage since freshman year of college.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#39;center&#39;&gt;
  &lt;img align=&#39;center&#39; src=&#39;/images/mileage.png&#39; width=&#39;25%&#39; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dots indicate races I&amp;#8217;ve run. Red means bad, yellow alright, and green is good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The four drops to zero miles are the one to two week breaks I take after the end of cross country and track seasons. Using these drops, we can break the graph into five curves:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freshman Cross Country&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Freshman Indoor Track + Outdoor Track&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Sophomore Summer + Cross Country&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Sophomore Indoor Track + Outdoor Track&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Junior Summer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My freshman year was horrendous: one good race, one alright race, six bad races. But, it was followed by a breakout sophomore year. I still don&amp;#8217;t know what caused my huge success The paradox is that mileage and workouts were relatively similar. Sleep and a few other variables were slightly better my sophomore year, but it doesn&amp;#8217;t seem sufficient for a breakout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the questions I ask myself is whether the mileage buildup I had my freshman year, which doubled my high school weekly mileage, resulted in short-term failures but longer-term success. It is my current hypothesis, but again it doesn&amp;#8217;t seem sufficient in itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fifth, unfinished curve represents my current buildup coming into junior year cross country. I have focused on slow mileage building, but I am in significantly worse shape than the same time my sophomore year. It&amp;#8217;s hard to compare because I have not done workouts or races yet, so I may be fine. But if not, it&amp;#8217;s hard to see why the summer coming into my sophomore year was so much more successful than the one coming into my junior year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good, bad, and alright races also seem unpredictable. Whether or not I take a down week (i.e. downward sloping on the graph) does not have a definitive effect. That being said, the sample size is so small it&amp;#8217;s hard to make any judgments from it alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My whole point for this post is that running is complicated&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:2&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:2&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Success is easily defined: how fast can you run. But, no one has figured out the science behind becoming faster. It takes a combination of mileage and interval training, but to what extent in each direction? Also, there are so many other factors affecting races: weather, mental state, sleep, and luck just to name a few. However, I think these deviations are more prevalent in runners than other sports because of the small sample size of races and that success is based on an individual (see: Law of Large Numbers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#39;/machine-learning-and-politics&#39;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, I discussed the dichotomy between the hedgehog and the fox. For individuals or small training groups, one needs to be a fox and tailor plans to the specific athlete. It&amp;#8217;s important to note that Paavo Nurmi and Arthur Lydiard (the godfathers of the two schools of running) were more fox-ish (I couldn&amp;#8217;t bring myself to say foxy) than we make them out to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hedgehogs, those who believe in big ideas, do indeed have success in the running world. But, it&amp;#8217;s when they have a huge team and just run them through a system. With enough runners, there will be some who emerge as stars. High school running powerhouses are notorious for doing this. However, because the training wasn&amp;#8217;t catered to the individual, their athletes usually fall short of expectations in college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the small dataset of training and its impact on races, no one has determined a set formula to succeed. Perhaps a larger dataset will shed light into the science of the subject. But perhaps there is an art involved, and that&amp;#8217;s what makes it so alluring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;div class=&#39;footnotes&#39;&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:1&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did not mean to make it sound Field of Dreams - esque&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:1&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:2&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know of a runner from DI running powerhouse, University of Portland. Despite the fact that he ran 120 miles per week (40 - 50 more than me), our collegiate personal bests in the 5000m are equivalent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:2&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/trial-of-miles-miles-of-trials&quot;&gt;The Trial of Miles, Miles of Trials&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on September 03, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Machine Learning and Politics]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/machine-learning-and-politics" />
  <id>/machine-learning-and-politics</id>
  <published>2016-08-21T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-08-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Machine learning promises us precise and accurate predictions. From the past movies you’ve seen on Netflix, what will you want to see in the future? Depending on your genetic makeup, what treatment should you take? Based on the current game board in Go, what is the best move to play?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Policymakers are becoming increasingly split on party lines among how to best allocate resources. In &lt;em&gt;Whatever It Takes&lt;/em&gt;, Paul Tough describes the age-old question on how to solve the educational achievement gap. Conservatives believe those in the low-income bracket are lazy, while liberals attribute their failures to insufficient government support. The debate on the relationship between education and poverty is ongoing, and as a result, we don’t have a definitive way of using education to end the poverty cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter machine learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning may actually be able to determine the cause of the achievement gap. Imagine a longitudinal study that tracks as much student data as possible. I’m talking data ranging from their IQ to the zip code they were born in to the background of their family members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we get all this data, unleash learning algorithms on them. We’ll try to predict an attribute like a student&amp;#8217;s test scores or whether they graduate from college. If our learner has a decent accuracy rate, we may have solved the achievement gap. Now, just start with a target student and tweak their characteristics to see what results in higher scores or a better graduation rate. Policymakers will then finally understand what exactly we need to change instead of relying on &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; intuitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now yes, there are many caveats here. First, we need to get an enormous amount of data for this experiment to work. Is it possible to do get enough data that does not violate privacy concerns but is able to sufficiently train the learner? Next, our learner is not guaranteed to be a good predictor. If not, is it because the problem is unsolvable or we don’t have enough data? And perhaps most importantly, even if we train an accurate learner, will policymakers concede if they disagree with it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are essential questions to address, but I don’t think they should obscure the bigger picture: machine learning has the potential to greatly reduce partisan gridlock in Congress! Policy aims to solve problems, and it’s often unclear that it actually does. In an ideal world, policy isn’t about rhetoric but rather delivering tangible results. Machine learning may very well be our best shot to figure out what is the right thing to do. If we accept that actual progress is more important than saving face, machine learning will change policy work drastically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Nate Silver recounts in &lt;em&gt;The Signal and the Noise&lt;/em&gt;, there are hedgehogs and foxes. Hedgehogs, like politicians, believe one theory explains everything. Foxes, on the other hand, believe that there are many variables you must look at. He attributes much of his success&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:1&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:1&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; with election predictions to his foxlike nature. Machine learning promises to be a fox and analyze the minute details. If trained right, it will understand what variables &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; affect problems like the achievement gap and thus give us detailed recommendations on how to end it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the excitement of machine learning has been with science and software companies. But, governments have a lot to gain by deploying such algorithms on us&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:2&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:2&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Yes, there are privacy issues to be considered. Yes, algorithms probably will not bring closure on issues like abortion and the death penalty. And yes, there will still be debates about how to best implement the proposed solutions. But, it is definitely within our reach to solve problems like the achievement gap. That in itself is enough justification to use machine learning in the policy world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;div class=&#39;footnotes&#39;&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:1&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is, before Trump&amp;#8217;s GOP Nomination&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:1&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:2&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is in no way an endorsement of the NSA data-collection scheme. There is some personal data that should be analyzed and some that shouldn&amp;#8217;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:2&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/machine-learning-and-politics&quot;&gt;Machine Learning and Politics&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on August 21, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[RoboTutor]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/robotutor" />
  <id>/robotutor</id>
  <published>2016-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;RoboTutor is a project at Carnegie Mellon&amp;#8217;s Robotics Institute aiming to enable students ages 7 - 10 with basic arithmetic, reading, and writing skills. This project is the university&amp;#8217;s entry into the Global Learning XPRIZE Competition, which is aiming to solve the shortage of teachers in developing countries through open-source technology. I designed and implemented the tutor for addition, subtraction, and multiplication. In addition, I designed the persona of the tutor that will act as a motivational agent to the student throughout the learning process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked on this project under the supervision of Professor &lt;a href=&#39;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~mostow/&#39;&gt;Jack Mostow&lt;/a&gt;. For more information, &lt;a href=&#39;http://www.cmu.edu/scs/robotutor/&#39;&gt;click here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/robotutor&quot;&gt;RoboTutor&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on August 04, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[From China to Tuscaloosa]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/from-china-to-tuscaloosa" />
  <id>/from-china-to-tuscaloosa</id>
  <published>2016-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When someone talks about &amp;#8220;zen&amp;#8221;, the last thing you think about is college football. Especially good ole&amp;#8217; SEC football. But, there is an interesting life philosophy that connects the Zen master and ancient Greeks to the California mountain climbers and Alabama football players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yvon Chouninard, avid climber and founder of the Patagonia clothing company, writes in his memoir, &lt;em&gt;Let My People Go Surfing&lt;/em&gt;, that he has&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;been a student of Zen philosophy of many years. In Zen archery, for example, you forget about the goal - hitting the bull&amp;#8217;s eye - and instead focus on all the individual movements involved in shooting an arrow. You practice your stance, reaching back and smoothly pulling an arrow out of the quiver, notching it on the string, controlling your breathing, and letting the arrow release itself. If you&amp;#8217;ve perfected all the elements, you can&amp;#8217;t help but hit the center of the target. The same philosophy is true for climbing mountains. If you focus on the &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; of climbing, you&amp;#8217;ll end up on the summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For college football fans, this concept of focusing on the &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; may seem all too familiar. Nick Saban, legendary coach of the Alabama Crimson Tide, has made it a trademark of his coaching philosophy ever since being introduced to the concept by a Michigan State psychology professor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, the input is what matters. It is the only thing you can control. Focus on doing your role, step by step, and the rest will fall into place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monte Burke explains in his biography, &lt;em&gt;Saban: The Making of a Coach&lt;/em&gt;, that &amp;#8220;Saban constantly admonished his players not to think about lifting a trophy at the end of the season, but focus on conditioning, reps in practice, and on keeping their grades up to remain eligible to play.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#39;http://www.secsports.com/article/14561357/nick-saban-process&#39;&gt;SEC Sports article&lt;/a&gt; states that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Process is simply Saban&amp;#8217;s core belief that the willingness to prepare in a methodical, daily basis is the key to success. Saban believes those who focus on the result and not the consistent preparation that is necessary to achieve the result are doomed to be disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;It&amp;#8217;s about committing yourself to being the best you can be on that particular day,&amp;#8221; said Saban. &amp;#8220;Improvement is a steady march and you have to be committed to it.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ryan Holiday drew parallels between &amp;#8216;the Process&amp;#8217; and Stoic philosophy in his book, &lt;em&gt;The Obstacle is the Way&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:1&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:1&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Stoicism advocates for not letting the results of actions dictate your feelings. Results are products of your inputs as well as some other, uncontrollable inputs. If these uncontrollable inputs go against you, failure is not necessarily your fault. Thus, if you are doing the best to your ability and still fail, so be it. There is a degree of luck involved in the success of every venture, and one must obey the laws of probability.&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:2&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:2&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until I read Chouinard&amp;#8217;s memoir, I thought &amp;#8216;the Process&amp;#8217; was a relatively obscure and isolated idea. The fact that it is a part of Zen philosophy and mountain climbing culture, in addition to SEC football and Stoicism, just might point to the range and importance of the concept. It is an effective and successful philosophy that can and should be used by anyone with a goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common criticism I hear of American philosophy departments is that they only emphasize Western philosophy. It would be interesting learning more about Eastern philosophies or more obscure Western philosophies (e.g. Stoicism) to learn about new ideas and potential parallels. It may even increase the popularity of philosophy.&lt;sup id=&#39;fnref:3&#39;&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;#fn:3&#39; rel=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;div class=&#39;footnotes&#39;&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:1&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stoicism is often misrepresented as showing no emotion and having no feeling. It is much more complex than this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:1&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:2&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Referencing probability while explaining a philosophy is what happens when you read too much Eliezer Yudkowsky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:2&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&#39;fn:3&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t mind philosophy being considered impractical, but I&amp;#8217;m also a philosophy minor. That being said, the ratio of computer science to philosophy majors at my school is 16:1, and I go to a liberal arts college.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#39;#fnref:3&#39; rev=&#39;footnote&#39;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/from-china-to-tuscaloosa&quot;&gt;From China to Tuscaloosa&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on June 02, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lies, Damned Lies, and Statistics]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/lies-damned-lies-and-statistics" />
  <id>/lies-damned-lies-and-statistics</id>
  <published>2016-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With big data and numbers pervading into social science research nowadays, it is becoming increasingly important that we start educating individuals on how to create and interpret statistical inferences. Too many times an author will (perhaps unintentionally) use ambiguous language to suggest a conclusion that does not actually follow from their data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago, I read Michelle Alexander&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;The New Jim Crow: Mass Incarceration in the Age of Colorblindness&lt;/em&gt;. This book truly lived up to all the hype and is a must-read for anyone who has ever pondered about mass incarceration and the criminal justice system in the United States today. Alexander lays out her bold conclusion upfront, but she backs up it well in her arguments throughout the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My inner statistician, however, did pick up on some questionable uses of data. While these points were very minor compared to the scope of the whole book, they serve as good examples of the potential to misinterpret statistics in current literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During one instance, she pointed how &amp;#8220;white youth were actually the &lt;em&gt;most likely&lt;/em&gt; of any racial or ethnic group to be guilty of illegal drug possession.&amp;#8221; It is easy to glance over this statement and think that it is straightforward, but her language describing her data is actually ambiguous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, two different interpretations are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A larger percentage of white youth population possesses illegal drugs compared to the black youth population&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that a youth possesses drugs, they have a higher chance of being white than black&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First glance of the original statement seems to point to (1), but her data could actually represent (2). And, if the latter is the case, the statement is trivial. There are more white youths than black youths in the United States. If drug possession is identically distributed among the races, we expect more illegal drug possessors will be white rather than black due to population demographics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I believe Alexander wrote the original statement to support the claim that black youth aren&amp;#8217;t worse than white youth, it can be interpreted at first glance to be arguing that white youth are worse than black youth. It is unclear what she means, and statements of this magnitude need to be rigorously backed up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexander similarly remarks later that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, in New Jersey, whites were almost twice as likely to be found with illegal drugs or contraband as African Americans, and few times as likely to be found with contraband as Latinos. Although whites were more likely to be guilty or carrying drugs, they were far less likely to be viewed as suspicious, resulting in relatively few stops, searches, and arrests of whites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, the first half of this statement is as ambiguous as the previous example - it can definitely fall under either interpretation. I believe the point she wishes to make is that there is a discrepancy between actual drug possession and police searching. This conclusion is valid and follows from her presentation of the data. However, again, it is easy for the reader to gather that whites are the worst racial group when it comes to drug usage. There is nothing wrong with that statement if it&amp;#8217;s true, but it is unclear from her language if it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to completely criticize Alexander, I did applaud her for pointing out one statistical misinterpretation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As much as half of state prisoners are violet offenders, but that statistic can easily be misinterpreted. Violent offenders tend to get longer prison sentences that nonviolent offenders, and therefore comprise a much larger share of the prison population than they would if they had earlier release dates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexander highlights that data is not i.i.d. (independently, identically distributed). Rather, each prisoner does not have the same sentence length. Thus, any statistic that aggregates the state of a prison at any one instance is not representative of the prison system because those with longer sentences are overrepresented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vague statistical language can imply certain conclusions when they actually mean something different. It is both up to the writer and the reader to be skeptical and closely analyze any such use. Too many times members of the media, especially news organizations, can spin numbers to fit their agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On an ending note, &lt;em&gt;The New Jim Crow&lt;/em&gt; is a phenomenal book and has established Alexander as a key civil rights advocate of this decade. The amount of racism in the law enforcement and criminal justice system is at too high of a level. While we have made so much progress over the past fifty years, it is obviously not enough.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lies-damned-lies-and-statistics&quot;&gt;Lies, Damned Lies, and Statistics&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on May 20, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[GreenMon]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/greenmon" />
  <id>/greenmon</id>
  <published>2016-05-19T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mayank Agrawal</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>mayankagrawal96@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;GreenMon is a peer-to-peer cluster management system designed to reduce power consumption. It dynamically powers nodes on and off in response to changing system usage. Benefits of peer-to-peer compared to the usual model of cluster with a master node include both better scalability and fault tolerance. GreenMon’s protocols utilize randomization to bypass any additional communication between nodes and thus keep the system lightweight. While ideally designed for remote clusters, it is general enough to be used on any LAN cluster. Preliminary simulations show that GreenMon can reduce power consumption by eighty percent on a schoolwide lab cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked on this project alongside classmates Owen Kephart and Oscar Chen. We were lucky to work under the guidance of &lt;a href=&#39;https://www.cs.swarthmore.edu/~newhall/&#39;&gt;Tia Newhall&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#39;https://www.cs.swarthmore.edu/~knerr/&#39;&gt;Jeff Knerr&lt;/a&gt;. The full paper is &lt;a href=&#39;/assets/docs/greenmon.pdf&#39;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenmon&quot;&gt;GreenMon&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Mayank Agrawal at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Mayank&lt;/a&gt; on May 19, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>